Today, I sat down with Austin Federa, co-founder of DoubleZero.
DoubleZero is a new network of physical infrastructure to make blockchains and ultimately other internet
technologies run faster.
Austin started DoubleZero last year after spending four years in senior roles at the
Solana Foundation, solving infrastructure problems of how to make Solana an exceptionally
fast and cheap money movement layer.
DoubleZero was born out of that first-hand experience.
Austin brings an incredibly informed view on the intersection of blockchains, internet
infrastructure, and market coordination.
It was a pleasure to have this conversation and I hope you enjoy listening.
Matt Walsh and Nick Carter are partners at Castle Island Ventures.
All of these expressed by them or the guests on this podcast are solely their opinions
and do not reflect the opinions of Castle Island Ventures.
Guests and hosts may maintain positions in the assets discussed in this podcast.
You should not treat any opinion expressed by anyone on this podcast as a specific inducement
to make a particular investment or follow a particular strategy but only as an expression
of their personal opinion.
This podcast is for informational purposes only.
Austin, thanks for sitting down with us today.
I have heard a lot about DoubleZero and excited to dive in as well as about some of your experience.
Would you mind just kicking off with what is DoubleZero for people who might be unfamiliar,
vaguely familiar, or trying to familiarize themselves?
So DoubleZero is a crypto infrastructure project but it's actual infrastructure, not just software
systems because usually when crypto people talk about infrastructure, they're really
just talking about software.
What we are building and have built out is a high performance global fiber network optimized
for the types of problems that high performance distributed systems have as opposed to the
types of problems that you see on the public internet today which are more about reach
than they are about performance.
So we have 10 independent contributors that are all contributing fiber to the DoubleZero
network and there's a blockchain based protocol that sits on top of that that helps orchestrate
link coordination, reward payouts, and the distributed management of that system.
There's an irony because I think in AI and in other facets of technology, data centers
have really started to take popular mind share and people are focused on the hardware infrastructure
but it feels very much like something people miss on the crypto side.
If you think about it, pretty much every large software company is in hardware now and they're
not in hardware because they want to be.
Facebook did not start building its own servers and then building its own data centers and
then building its own high speed subsea fiber because they wanted to.
They got into it because the existing market wouldn't service their needs for scale and
they're not running subsea cables through the Philippines out of the goodness of their
hardware because it's a plus EV business line.
They're doing it so they can sell ads.
They want Instagram reels to load more quickly so you keep scrolling so you see more ads
and at a certain point of scale, the way to solve a problem of there being slow internet
in the Philippines is just to go build it yourself.
And time and time again, we see software companies making this transition from a pure software
play into hardware that supports their software, which eventually becomes a competitive advantage.
For years, crypto just wasn't there because a lot of the major use cases were financial
and those use cases we know and love and are great, but at the end of the day, we've gotten
to a place where if crypto is really going to start competing with traditional finance
systems and other types of high performance distributed systems, it needs to be using
the same tools and technologies.
We don't think of Google as a distributed systems company, but it is Google is run in
dozens of data centers all over the world.
Now it's all run by Google and it's all linked by Google's private fiber, but you wouldn't
get the experience of YouTube or any other Google product if they didn't have this high
performance fiber network under the hood.
But in crypto, we can't just say, oh great, we're going to use Amazon's network or Google's
network or someone like that because you wouldn't have to trust that network.
If 00 were built as a centralized company with a global fiber network that we ran and
managed, you shouldn't trust it.
The reason you can trust 00's fiber network is it's got 10 independent contributors,
it's got censorship resistance, it's got all of the things that you would expect from
a blockchain based project, and also the internet's a lot more centralized than people realize
too.
I completely agree and that alternative would completely defeat the purpose of blockchains
in the first place.
You might as well run databases at that point.
Yeah, it depends what you're using blockchain for.
There's this knock that I feel like some people have sometimes about, oh, blockchain systems
are just databases and you're like, well, first off, yeah, everything is just databases.
The New York Stock Exchange is just a database at the end of the day.
The real unlock with blockchain is it's the most perfect system of accounting we've ever
created.
It doesn't require an external auditor, it doesn't require trusted execution environments,
it doesn't require external validation of system integrity, it is internally consistent
in how it validates data, and it has all these other characteristics of being able to be
run anywhere in the world and being permissionless.
But part of the reason we are seeing more corporations adopting blockchain technology,
even if they're doing it in a fully centralized way, is because you can cut out a lot of the
Web 2 detritus that we've had to stick on to these internet protocols to make them secure.
We all know SOC2 is a joke and doesn't actually mean anything, but it's like this arbitrary
stamp of approval that the business people stuck on a bunch of software because we fundamentally
can't trust software because the way that Web 1 and Web 2 software was built was that
trust was an external property brought into it.
In blockchain, trust is an intrinsic property to all these system designs, and that means
that Visa's now got a program exploring building in L1, Stripe has a whole program building
in L1, Circle obviously has a whole program building in L1, and it's not because they
want to launch a token and raise more money, they're all very valuable companies in their
own right, it's because they can actually reduce operational overheads by adopting blockchain
technology.
Completely agree.
And when we have those on-chain systems which will continue to merge under the guise of
those companies, they're going to be looking for that level of performance optimization
that we were talking about where you had the cloud computing rush and you just had this
major improvement to underlying performance in the traditional tech world.
So in that vein is the right way to think about double zero that you have this distributed
hardware network sitting underneath and then an on-chain coordination layer on top.
Yeah, that's the right way to think about it.
And depending on the level of abstraction you go, there's two or three different layers.
But one of the things that we think is really important here is this is not a system just
built for blockchain.
So it's always been possible to build a multi-party high-performance fiber network.
These things actually exist.
Go West is an example of this.
It's a consortium run by a number of HFT firms.
The thing there though is access to that fiber and that microwave tower system is quite controlled
and quite expensive to get access to.
So you can think about the cloud revolution was not a revolution in technology, it was
a revolution in business model.
At the end of the day, a hypervisor with a 20% performance overhead is a pretty uncompelling
design for system architecture.
People forget that the cloud is actually quite slow.
It's very compute inefficient to run stuff in the cloud compared to like a bare metal
service system.
The advantage of the cloud is the management layer on top of it and the ability to go to
AWS and say, I need 500 servers and have them deployed within an hour.
That's something you can't get through another type of system.
So in double zero, we don't have a performance overhead like the cloud has.
We are giving folks direct access to this fiber.
But if you wanted to go and build a global fiber network yourself, it would take you
two years minimum.
And you'd need a staff of at least five people who've done this before to actually be able
to go out and do the site sourcing and all the contracting and agreements.
It's a very complicated process.
But with something like double zero, you can just connect in and say, hey, I've got a server
running in CC2 in Tokyo and I need to connect that in to NY4 because I need to send a bunch
of data that's either low latency or I need to send a large volume of data that the public
internet can't really support.
And you can do that basically on demand.
And our first application of this technology stack is blockchain because blockchain is
the place where you have two important components.
You have demand and you have capital.
So blockchains will really benefit from high performance connectivity and blockchain operators
receive pretty good amounts of revenue for operating their systems.
So if they can squeak 10 basis points of performance out of the thing, they're going
to do it.
So it has that same characteristic of a high frequency trading firm, but it has a distributed
systems problem that a high frequency trading firm does not.
The incremental benefit to blockchain performance is very valuable.
I want to double click on a point you made because I think it's really important and
under discussed.
Can you touch on the market dynamics for why high performance fiber networks have not
permeated to being used by everyone, why everyone doesn't have access to them?
How has that existed to date?
And how does that inform where internet systems are high performance, less performance?
How has that shaped that?
So we're very used to talking about network effect systems when we think about anything
in blockchain or web 2.
High performance private networking is an anti-network effect business.
If I am jump trading and I have a high performance link from Chicago to New York, I don't want
Citadel or DRW on that link.
I actually want to keep it just for myself.
It's a competitive advantage.
Exactly.
And you don't see that in data center construction for the most part.
You don't see that in server construction.
It's not like NVIDIA is getting proprietary chips and just using them for themselves.
They're selling it to other people.
Our business model is built on distribution, whereas a lot of the traditional financial
space, the business model is built on proprietary access or proprietary data or proprietary performance.
So even if you're a company like eBay, you are running a private fiber network, but you
have to be the size of a company like eBay to actually have the capital, to have the
overhead to hire all these people.
It is exactly how when a company makes a transition from the cloud back to bare metal data center,
they need to hire a ton of people because that is not a turnkey software managed service.
The real world is just a lot messier than software.
Cables get cut by ship anchors or they go down for maintenance or you have a switch that
burns out in a data center and you have to do a failover and someone has to, at the end
of the day, go to that location and move a thing and touch a thing and replace a product.
And all of these reasons basically create massive overhead.
The other piece too is you're dealing with a hundred different countries and a number
of different languages and the different legal systems and the problems of international
payment transfers are nothing compared to international data transfers.
The amount of different regulations you have to go through, there's stuff that's totally
not allowed in the EU that if you do it in the US is totally fine.
There's other things that the US wants you to do that the EU will be mad if you do.
It's a very messy complicated system in part because of government overhead and in part
because it is just something that is in the physical world and things in the physical
world are much harder to automate or scale than stuff in the software world.
So typically what happens now is you have these carriers and most of the carriers are
owned by private equity firms.
So what they really want to do is throw off eight to nine percent returns per year.
So they're not investing ahead of time in a lot of infrastructure.
But cables are basically run at ninety to ninety five percent capacity twenty four seven.
You can think of it as just in time bandwidth.
Really truly the way that these companies think of the internet is as a pipeline and
supply chain problem.
It's similar to how energy grids are operated.
There's no incentive to have a ton of burst capacity because all that burst capacity is
is a cost when you're in a business that's on cost optimization.
So one of the things that we're able to do with double zero is just change the entire
revenue model.
And tokens are really required for the alignment necessary in this type of system.
But also we're just massively expanding the time of what access can be to these types
of systems.
So our hope is that we have and we've already seen this on a small level with our contributors.
But we expect over the long term people are going to be installing new fiber cables under
the ocean just to participate in double zero because right now we have this divorce between
the physical layer and the value add monetary layer on top of it.
Time ordering a semi trailer to move stuff from New York to San Francisco doesn't matter
if it's full of wine or if it's full of gravel.
The cost is the same per pound even though what's in it is a very different value.
So because in blockchain we have to reach hundreds of points around the world.
No company can actually build out enough fiber capacity to do that.
There's not many financial centers in the world.
A trading firm can wire them all up.
They can't wire up every data center where blockchain stuff is run, let alone every
data center where CDNs or AI technology is run.
So because of that they need to be involved in a network like this.
And the minute you have that type of system you're able to actually have a revenue model
that supports portions of value transferred over the systems, not just dump pipes.
Yeah, that all makes a lot of sense.
I have several points I want to ask you about in response.
The first one is probably if you're in and around the business of more performant fiber
optic networks but even in performant hardware in general that sits underneath these systems
you're tussling with the incentives behind either owning this vertical stack where in
the jump example you profit through some business model that you've built on top of your max
performant layer because you can outperform everyone or you're productizing your performance.
You're choosing one of those two which is like keep for yourself versus sell as a product
because others will want it.
And in that view this seems conducive in certain market structures to vertical monopolies
where people would want to own the most performant part at every layer of the stack.
You guys have a great layering on your website.
I encourage people to look at where he talks about the seven layers of the blockchain stack
for example.
I could see a market structure to that point where someone would want to own every part
especially if they feel like they have a competitive advantage say on the hardware layer.
Do you see that as likely to happen let's say in the blockchain industry for example.
So the natural end state of many of these systems you can think through as vertical integration
that is the natural end state of basically any economic system is complete vertical integration
with the absence of human faulty.
There is no reason a company in a dominant position should ever lose market share.
We see Coinbase doing it to be realistic.
Totally.
The Coinbase thing is an interesting case study.
So what we see here is that the scale someone needs to actually vertically integrate all
of those systems is quite high and the more vertically integrated a system you get the
lower performance each layer in that vertical stack tends to be.
This is not a law but this is a generally observed concept is that the more vertically
integrated a company is the less attention they pay to each individual component.
And this is really true in anything that is in the financial space and because at the
end of the day the relative performance gains that at each piece in the stack that you can
get don't impact your overall bottom line as much they do for an independent actor.
I think this is one of the things that's not well understood with folks who are like break
up the big monopolies.
There is a component of something like a Google where you can argue if it's monopolistic
or not.
What's very hard to argue is Google has the best offerings almost across the board everything
Google offers there's a better alternative to it.
This is true of JP Morgan.
This is true of Coinbase.
This is true of AWS.
This is true of pretty much any fully vertically integrated system.
This is true of Tesla.
All of these components they may have a one stop shop for everything but what they're
able to do at each layer of that stack is minimize.
The reason that this can be a problem in the traditional space is because you have arbitrary
barriers and interoperability.
Those arbitrary barriers and interoperability are things like I message just doesn't work
on an Android phone or the classic thing there.
In crypto we don't have that and Coinbase is trying very hard to build a fully vertically
integrated product where now there's wallets on base that you cannot move back to Ethereum
but fundamentally the assets are still fungible and movable.
So we see this all the time now where you'll have data centers that have a large amount
of Solana stake in them and then a competitor will spin up and they'll be a little bit cheaper
or they'll be able to have about 10 basis points of additional revenue and you can just
watch the validators migrate to the new data center.
These are very portable industry.
This is part of why the validator as a service business or the RPC business is a pretty bad
business statistically.
As someone who used to work for bison trails these businesses are very hard because the
portability of your customers is extremely high.
So I think we are a ways away from having to worry about that type of vertical integration
in crypto because it's mostly open source software and it's mostly highly portable
systems that you don't need to rely on some external trust validation for.
I may not be comfortable moving my money out of JP Morgan into a startup bank.
Not because the JP Morgan has a better product but because the name of JP Morgan carries
a certain amount of gravitas with it.
Realistically that's only a problem when you're dealing with systems that require trust and
if the system doesn't require trust like in the case of blockchain you don't necessarily
have that portability limiting factor.
I like your assertion that vertically integrated businesses won't be frankly at the cutting
edge at each layer.
I'm curious for your view on how industry positioning and regulatory capture plays into
that though because I think of something like telecommunications in the 2000s which somewhat
famously was very difficult to break into for companies which were trying to innovate
and there was a sharp reduction in the amount of venture funding that went into it I think
just because people started to give up a little bit.
So granted the vertically integrated larger players won't be the most innovative do you
worry that it can become too difficult to disintermediate them even with a better offering.
So I think the telecom regulatory capture wasn't actually on the regulatory side.
If you look at what happened there the access barriers were basically all of the state and
local level they weren't at the federal level which is not what you typically expect banking
regulation is captured at the federal level it's not captured at the state level.
The problem that we ran into starting in the 2000s is we just got allergic to building
stuff the same problems that mean you can't build a pipeline you can't build transmission
lines is the reason you couldn't build fiber lines is that these systems tend to all co-locate
with one another you're putting in transmission lines great we can put some fiber beneath it
or you're putting in a pipeline great we can run a bunch of fiber alongside it and what we
saw is just nimbyism taken over and not letting you build anything and I think that's a different
type of problem than the typical thing we think of as regulatory capture like in the
financial space where it's just the banking lobby has made it such that it's almost impossible
to get a new banking charter and that's a different type of regulatory capture than
I think we see in the telecom space. What about the issue you have where to be crude
disintermediating AWS would be inherently difficult because just the level of capture
that they have with maybe strong army or compelling partners to continue to work with them?
I actually think the mode of AWS is the tragedy of computer science over the last 20 years
which is that people don't know how anything works anymore and this is not AWS I actually
don't think there's a lot of strong arming from the cloud providers there's some sure but the cloud
provider is actually a fairly competitive market nowadays it is the fact that people just don't
learn how anything works anymore if you talk to a modern web 2 engineer versus a high frequency
trading engineer they're almost entirely different species at this point the work and concerns of
someone who works for a trading firm they would never be caught dead virtualizing anything because
the performance overhead you get is they don't even use kernel networking the overhead that you
have to do because of all these layers of software abstractions on top of them you listen to Kevin
Bowers who's one of the chief research scientists over at jump talk about how a modern processor
works in the way modern compilers work and a solid 20 percent of their job is just stripping away
all of the crap that people have built to make programming easy so they can actually talk to
the hardware and you think about this as they have this whole thing about tile architecture and
tile architecture is not a new concept it's actually an old concept but if you look at a
modern processor it has 24 32 cores 64 cores and if you just try and run stuff on it the management
software at a very low level just randomly assigns different tasks to different cpus and when you're
trying to optimize for performance you have to think about the physical signal pathways within
the chip and how data flows through the chip and how the infinite band on the inside of a chip
actually manages data flow and so if you have one process on this corner of the chip and one process
on this corner of the chip it actually takes a meaningful amount of time for the data to get
from one side of the chip to the other because it has to get signal boosted as it moves through the
silicon layers the speed of light is actually a factor at this point too so you get into a place
where we're bleeding out so much performance in modern systems because people don't know how
they work and they're not thinking at that low level anymore well it's they haven't had to build it
it's been there for them yeah the mode that the cloud providers have is that most modern software
engineers are lazy and it's the classic thing of like when apple pulled everyone over from writing
in c to writing in swift for programs yes apple can do magic on the compiler level to make things
quite performant but there's also a whole skill set that's lost for people that want to build even
more performant programs and you see this even on a network like salana where folks were writing a
bunch of stuff in anchor which is the subtraction language on top of it rust was the default high
performance for a while now c is the default high performance for writing salana programs and there's
actually some stuff that's been written in assembly and you have to be willing to get that
low level on performance optimization and part of this is the fault of vcs where there's a whole
incentive structure in vc which is don't worry about costs just worry about scale and if that is
the structure you're building under then who cares if your server bill goes from 800 thousand dollars
to 8 million dollars because you've grown 10x and growth is all that matters the problem though is
you see all of these companies they hit ipo and then suddenly they have to do a bunch of cost
downing on their infrastructure but they have no dna and they have no expertise to do it internally
and it's a huge transformation they have to go through and we saw my friend worked for etsy back
in i think this was probably 2014-15 and they had done a migration to the cloud they had this
incredible architecture set up in aws but etsy's got two to three percent gross margin business
they're taking transaction fees on a bunch of payment processing and some very smart person
there looked and said our aws bill is not going down this thing is increasing at seven to ten
percent per year as amazon raises prices we need to move out of the cloud so part of his job there
was orchestrating a giant migration from the cloud back to bare metal servers that were run in two
different data centers one in new jersey one in i think somewhere in colorado and they massively
reduced their cost over the short term but the delta there if you look at the average price
of something on aws it is outpacing inflation which is not what you would expect from plamor's
law type perspective but it's because people are willing to pay for it and the companies that are
willing to put the work into optimizing and moving back that is a far more effective form of cost
reduction than swapping out all your customer service people with ai agents it's the boring stuff
that people get wrong i think in the last 10 years too there was this software infatuation
and the successful venture stories or startup stories were things like etsy to your point
Shopify just break out software applications the most part that scaled revenue really quickly
and from an objective perspective i think this is one of the things people actually take to
without being articulated about about elon mosque is that he's one of the people that has actually
taken this attention to things like hardware and systems which especially years ago what was really
not paid much attention to by startups as an example yeah i mean we look at what were all of
the sexy space companies doing not even before SpaceX but along that same lines a lot of them
were focused on software systems or things that were going to we're going to hand away
of how we get them into orbit once they're in orbit here's the skill set that this thing
offers and it was a very very different perspective to say look if we're gonna actually make space a
real thing we need to rethink the entire way that we built launch systems on the business model
rethink it on the engineering side rethink it take risks that the industry was historically not
willing to take because the number one customer for the industry historically was the US government
apart from the do d it's very risk averse even the do d is pretty risk averse nasa would tell you
they would rather spend 10 times more for something that have a 10 chance that it blows up in the
launch pad because the pr damage will do more damage to their budget than the cost overrun but
so that whole model shifting i really think it's a pretty good analogy for what we're doing with
double zero because we are shifting the entire business and cost rationale around private fiber
in a place that's really only been accessible to hft firms until now makes sense i want to draw a
through line i was going to come back to an element of double zero i want to pick your brain
on to which i think a through line here is these infrastructure systems particularly the lower
down you go in the stack which gets the hardware they tend to become stagnant i think just because
of how much has been built on top and to your point that we don't necessarily have a lot of
people who are thinking about innovating on this front and it's difficult how do you look at
from your perspective double zero perspective creating a low level infrastructure that can
innovate as opposed to become stagnant let's say even if you take on prominent market position in
five years so one of the things that we don't do is we don't offer any servers for people it is
really truly just fiber and some compute resources implemented through fpga but this is a thing that
salon has always been very good at and i was a very strong advocate of this way of thinking when i
was at the salon a foundation for the last four years was that we should build things as low level
as possible and with as few opinions as possible so this is really how we're approaching double
zero we are building a series of tools that people can use to do things that i have no idea what
they're going to do with so we can do things you can't do on the public internet and maybe it's
worth getting some of this offering stack but at the very basic level we have fatter pipes and we
have pipes that have lower latency than the public internet so you'll get 100 gigabytes of connectivity
as opposed to one and your latency will be 30 to 70 less than you'd get over the public internet
but we can also do things like run multicast over this network which is a technology of basically
hardware acceleration of packet replication so if you need to do something like propagate blockchain
state from one machine to 2000 machines today you have to send out 2000 copies of that data manually
with multicast you send out two copies of it and the network replicates the data in hardware
acceleration on its own and so it really is a send and forget it type of model which really changes
how performance systems can operate and it also reduces the penalty for not being the first one
that the system sends out data to we can also do things like insert precision timing into the network
so you can do things like timeline packets you can know exactly what time the packet hit the
edge of the network and so that's really useful in all sorts of financialization and trading
systems as well you can now time align when stuff comes into the network you can make sure that
every one of your validators has extremely precise clock systems and you know okay this event happened
here at this node we can now reconstruct the order that something should have happened based on
wall clock time not based on something else so there's a lot of these types of functions and
services that just are not available on the public internet i don't know what everyone's
going to build with them smarter people than me you're going to come up with really awesome
stuff you can build using this toolkit that's the same thing we saw at salona for years i don't
think anyone predicted that meme coins would be a huge thing on salona or that we'd have tokenized
stocks the point is that they could be you created that sandbox to your point i think it's a great
point and in the interest of better technology to be unopinionated to really be non vertical in a
way to improve on each layer of the stack do you find attention because i imagine a lot of software
engineers to your point want more of a spoon fed infrastructure solution where they have something
that probably is opinionated and that checks 10 boxes at once instead of one or two is that difficult
to wrestle with and relatedly who are you selling into with that in mind so this is one of the things
that about crypto that's just such a joy we don't have that problem in crypto the engineers who are
building stuff on salona are very happy to be getting into the very low level systems and they
like how much of this they're exposing i think a real analogy here is the rise of navidia and at
the time that navidia launched kuda which is their programming framework for accessing vector
processors on gpu's it was not the cool way to do it all of the work on compilers and all the work
on this system was really about how to make it easier to use and kuda's innovation was there's
actually a lot of really smart programmers out there that want to be able to directly address
things to hardware and what they allowed people to do is write in languages they were already
fairly familiar in but add a few flags that allow you to actually address the hardware directly
and kevin bauer's favorite example is dense matrix multiplication it's actually very hard to write
that in a non kuda system and it's a hello world example is basically how do you dense
matrix multiplication on a gpu so when we look around and we see oh well everyone's just building
stuff in software abstraction layers no one really wants to address the hardware like you're
saying people don't want to get this low level into the stuff well we basically find our the
systems that are going to need double zero and would benefit from its performance are already
thinking that way so maybe we fast forward three or four years and yeah we have to do some type of
more accessible abstraction layer or we have to have a bunch of coursework for how to actually
optimize infrastructure for double zero but the place we're at today those people find us
we don't have to go find them because they've been looking for something like this for a long time
it's almost an inadvertent benefit then let's take mean coin trading example because it forces
people to really prioritize high speed because how lucrative it can be whereas they're playing
of legacy internet apps that could frankly run milliseconds slower and i don't think people
would care that much yeah and that's fine that is the big differentiator here so a great example
of this is there's a new prop AMM on Solana humidify and what it basically did is they wrote the whole
AMM program basically in assembly it's using this tiny framework and because it's so small relative
to other programs and it requires so little compute units which are basically sort of a unit of
transaction processing on the Solana network it pays about six times the compute to fee ratio that
any other DeFi program on Solana pays and it still pays incredibly little to send each transaction
but because the ratio is so high validators you're like oh i'm absolutely going to process these
transactions first because they're really efficient and they get paid comparatively a ton what does
that mean well suddenly this prop trading AMM is the fastest AMM on Solana and they can quote
half a basis point or less we executed a trade yesterday on chain where we got 10 basis points
of basically fee and slippage in this process which is better than you can get from any OTC
desk or any centralized exchange and this was fairly significant size too this wasn't a $2,000
transaction or something like that and that type of performance we're going to see this widening
gap between traditional systems and blockchain systems because you can get this insane performance
and you don't need all the compliance and security overhead what other use cases adjacencies technologies
do you think double zero is most primed to improve upon to work with in the interim
I think there's a lot of the AI space that cares a lot about connectivity we're not going to be
servicing open AI or someone like that that's got billions of dollars to build their own data
centers and their own high-frequency fiber cables themselves but there's a whole bunch of companies
that are in between stage where they've got a technology advantage but they don't have the
expertise or the timing to go out and build data centers and build fiber connectivity between them
noose research is a great example of this they're usually like a second customer on a lot of these
big AI workloads but they waste a bunch of time syncing model data back and forth so if we can
change that sync time to five minutes as opposed to 20 minutes that's 15 minutes more processing
that they're going to get on their models every time there is another customer in that system
I think the other area we see are CDN systems so there's this group called Shelby which is the
storage network that's being built by a combination of Aptos and Jump and that's going to run on double
zero and because it needs multicasting of data and it needs fast access to data and these sorts of
things to be able to do CDNs in markets that are not well served by CDNs at the moment so I think
there's a lot of these different types of applications that we'll see trading is absolutely
one of them as well the highest profit most turnkey solution here is just if you are trading on a
distributed system you need to get data as quickly as you can to as many places in the world as you
can on this note and to touch more broadly on the business you have the fiber network that
you work with the 10 providers you mentioned and then you guys are a coordination layer ultimately
providing a service to customers how do you look at how value should flow between you
and your 10 I don't know if you'd call them clients or providers that sit underneath
what we basically run on is a different reward model than most blockchains do that more closely
resembles a proof of work system than a proof of stake system so we have a whole blog post on
the website about this is called proof of utility but we basically use Shapley values to determine
what is the incremental value each network link provides to the overall network graph
and the benchmark for this is the public internet so if your link that you're adding
does not beat the public internet it gets no rewards if it beats the public internet but
actually doesn't connect anywhere that paying customers in this case blockchain validators
or rpcs are operating in then it also doesn't get any rewards but if we do the math on this and we
say like okay if your network link didn't exist the network would be 20% worse then you receive 20%
of the rewards for that given epoch of time so we have this system where we are incentivizing
competition between fiber providers to always be trying to basically steal each other's market
share and the best way to steal someone's market share is to provide a more performant
infrastructure link at the same time validators and rpcs are the ones that are actually paying to
use this service and we're working on a percentage of revenue model basically so if we're taking
about 5% of block rewards and priority fees and mev in exchange for this higher performance system
now we're also not going to take that 5% unless we're making them at least 5% more profit and
that's our trade with folks is yeah you're going to give us some percentage of your earnings which
is going to be more than maybe you're used to paying but in net you're going to make more because
you're able to operate on this high performance infrastructure and as part of the value proposition
we've talked a lot about performance but to my understanding there's also a privacy aspect
at play here yeah so privacy is I would say more of a theoretical problem than a practical problem
on the internet today so if you are sending a trade on a blockchain right now that data is
moving over the public internet and it might be passing through 15 or 20 different providers as it
gets to its destination deep packet inspection is very good at the moment it is entirely possible
that someone is holding back some of your packets arbitrarily so they can try and front run you or
something along those lines now there's very little evidence of this actually happening today
but it is a real theoretical concern this is one of the reasons that traditional financial firms
don't use the public internet to trade on it's slow yes there's that but you're also leaking data
about what you're doing so part of the thing with double zero is we can actually provide
cryptographic assurances to folks of data that moves over the network and we can catch providers
that are holding back data so if we see hey it's supposed to take 64.3 milliseconds to get from here
to here sometimes it's taking this 167 milliseconds what are they doing and that sets off an alert
that we can go and investigate and see if someone is selectively holding back traffic or something
along those lines we also will be able to in the future offer traffic encryption as well we can do
this in such a way there's very very little overhead involved in that encryption so you're
usually in this trade-off game now of oh I can encrypt my data but it slows it down and if you're
on zoom who cares no one's going to care about that slowing down of data if you're trying to trade
it may become a meaningful slowdown understood I did want to ask you hitting on some of the
topics we discussed before do you and double zero ever have ambitions to become your own settlement
layer for assets I don't think so this is one of those classic things of I don't think that's where
our expertise lies I think that double zero we're in a much better position to simply
not compete with blockchains to instead onboard all of them to double zero and have 10 networks
running the million transactions per second and have a percent based model that just takes a small
cut of all of those in exchange for providing a ton of value add services there's a lot of
layer ones out there and I think you have to have a really credible architecture or thesis decision
about why yours would be better and if all our answer is is it would be better because it's running
on a high performance private fiber with hardware acceleration and technologies you can't get on
the public internet going back to the very first thing we were talking about about non-network
effect businesses in Trabfi why would I not want the network effect of Solana and Sui and Aptos
and mega ETH and Monad and Stripes L1 and ARC and all of these things operating on top of double
zero why would I ever limit our market to just people who are willing to adopt the double zero
chain it's a very clear case for me of grow the pie as opposed to trying to take a bigger slice of
it usually when you try and take a bigger slice of the pie as opposed to growing the pie you
actually end up with a smaller piece of pie you're pulling from a much smaller base the final
question I wanted to ask you what do you look at the end state of this segment of the market being
do you think that we have a host of call it luxury fiber networks that the applications that really
need them or those that are willing to pay can pay forward do you think we have this slow public
internet which still powers most of what we use where do you think we end up this may not be like
a closing topic we might go a little long here but we have to think back to 2020 because 2020
informs a huge amount of this and what we saw in 2020 was a very strong effort to de-platform
certain applications and certain ideas from the web to world and irrespective of what you think
about those efforts morally it turned out that when a social network got kicked off of AWS and
get kicked off of Cloudflare it was extremely difficult for them to run infrastructure let alone
if they got kicked off of DNS which is also a centralized thing run basically out of the United
States by one company what we basically saw was we already have this world you're talking about of
a two-tier infrastructure system the folks who can pay for Cloudflare and the folks who can pay for
AWS and the folks who can pay for Akamai their infrastructure is more performant and it doesn't
actually run on the public internet it runs on this entire private system that's completely opaque
that runs alongside the internet that you have to pay to access and also they can kick you off at
any moment for any reason because net neutrality also first off doesn't apply to the US anymore
but even if it did does not apply to private networks so you get into this place very quickly
where we have an internet where pretty much anyone in a few positions of power can monkey with how
the whole system works let alone the US government can just say hey and we saw the emails Facebook
take down these posts hey YouTube remove this video and that is a difference in sending a letter
to Facebook saying delete this content and sending a letter to YouTube saying delete this content
and sending a letter to Verizon saying lock this content is the only difference there is the political
will of the United States versus the political will of the Chinese Communist Party and I don't
want to hang my hat on that differentiation in an era where free speech is kind of a little bit
less than it used to be you compare the 90s to the 2020s in terms of free speech and we have less
of it now than we used to in a lot of ways so this is a long way of saying when we think about
these types of systems over the long term I want credibly neutral alternatives to the existing
communication systems and I want basically universal systems of prioritization so today it
is very hard to say if I'm epic games and I want to prioritize all the fortnight traffic so kids
can play more games and buy more skins my bottom line revenue can go up I basically have to go
around and bribe every ISP to do that you'd think there'd be a protocol in the internet this is I
want to pay more to make my data better you can't do that today so double zero really over a long
term time horizon our goal is to become the default prioritization layer for anyone anywhere that needs
to send data in a timely fashion I think the other piece we're looking at over the long term is
replacing TCP IP with public key private key encryption and verification right now the only
way that I know a server is correct is I'm verifying a SSL certificate which is issued by a third party
authority I actually don't care about routing to an IP address on a blockchain I don't actually
want to talk to the specific IP address I want to talk to this specific cryptographic signature
so we can just cut out the entire middle layer for lack of a better term and actually start routing
things through public private key cryptography and I think that is going to be a pretty big
unlock for the ability to unwind a lot of these centralized we literally call it a trust authority
that's what a CA is we can try and unwind some of these centralized trust components from the system
and actually increase competition at the end of the day I'm a capitalist maxi and I want more
competition and fewer access barriers to building systems that compete with one another to those
points do you think these base infrastructure layers are inherently monopolistic if not pushed
otherwise to the point of first off higher powers will want to control and they can do so
via the base infrastructure secondarily there aren't a lot of innovators do you think that's
just what we converge on if not for other efforts I think that is the story of every economic system
going back as long as we've had an economy it's like a central bank almost exactly yes there's
two things we've done very intentionally to combat this the first is it's a token project and the
beauty of a token project is no one owns bitcoin yeah there's a bunch of people who maintain it and
they have more power over and michael sailor has got more power over bitcoin than I do but at the
end of the day it is a giant consensus on how these things will work and function and that
applies to ethereum that applies to selana you can't block someone on a bitcoin to your point
earlier you can't block someone on bitcoin or you can block someone on bitcoin but it requires
you getting 51% of the rest of the bitcoin network on board with you these systems are still built on
trust but they're built on the trust of the crowd as opposed to the trust of an individual privileged
actor in a system you can still change something in the ethereum ledger but the amount of people
you need to get on board to facilitate that change it's like amending the constitution it's a very
high barrier and that actually creates a ton of security and the second component for us is this
proof of utility system where proof of stake systems can turn into an oligarchy at some point
where you just have oh i have 4% of selana so therefore i earn a ton of rewards even though
i'm not doing a ton of work with the proof of utility system it's very similar to bitcoin if you
have 10% of the hash power of bitcoin you're going to get 10% of the new blocks irrespective of if
you have michael sailor bags or if you own zero bitcoin so we've tried to build our system in a
way that encourages long-term competition and it also rewards folks who are able to put in that
little incremental advantage and actually i think the true mark of success for a system is if someone
with a better idea or better technology can plug into that system permissionlessly and earn
outsized rewards for outsized contribution yeah i completely agree austin it's been a pleasure
chatting what should people do if they want to learn more about double zero or explore working
with you guys in the context of their business or operation so double zero dot xyz as our main
website you can find out a bunch of information about main net beta which is launching at the end
of september you can connect a validator and run on it as well as get in touch with us if you have
fiber to contribute or any other crazy ideas you want to explore brilliant thank you again thank you
thanks for listening to another episode of on the brink with castle island to find out more
about castle island visit castle island dot vc to listen to all of our podcast episodes please
go to on the brink dash podcast dot com or just click on the tab in our website thanks for listening